<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: wwdc | theonlylars]]></title>
  <link href="http://theonlylars.com/blog/categories/wwdc/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://theonlylars.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-03-14T18:15:51-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://theonlylars.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Lars Anderson]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Post-WWDC]]></title>
    <link href="http://theonlylars.com/blog/2012/06/27/post-wwdc/"/>
    <updated>2012-06-27T23:34:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://theonlylars.com/blog/2012/06/27/post-wwdc</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>WWDC was a ton of fun.  One of my coworkers equated it to drinking from a fire-hose all week, and that’s exactly what it was like - hardly any time to process any of what you’re taught all week. The sessions were really good, being surrounded by others who do what you do was inspiring, and the labs gave me access to Apple engineers to ask them whatever I wanted.  I got some really good feedback on my <a href="http://larsacus.github.com/LARSAdController">iOS ad integration class</a>, as well as some help integrating auto layout with some existing projects. There is a ton of material that is not mentioned in the videos (and sometimes even in the documentation) about how a class functions or was built. This is when access to the engineers that actually build the API is infinitely useful.  I’ll definitely be more prepared next year.</p>

<p>For those wondering, the WWDC minty boost <em>did</em> in fact work to charge my devices (which was totally necessary every single day), but heated up the AA’s due to the current draw and re-melted the hot-glue that was protecting the PCB to the battery chassis. I only got one use out of it, but really didn’t need it any longer once you know to plug your phone in to charge at every opportunity.</p>

<p>It also humbles me as an engineer to be surrounded by so many people from all over the world who have gone on to do such publicly “great” things by comparison to what I feel like I’ve done.  Most of the work I do can’t be shown to anyone else as <em>my</em> work, so I often find myself longing for a very public application or open source project to put my name on. Something I can say that <em>I</em> built or had a significant impact in building and it’s something that millions of others love and find useful. All good things come in time to those who work hard, so we’ll see where the next few years takes me. But for someone who really likes being openly proud of his work instead of just knowing intrinsically that I worked on something public, private white-label consulting is difficult for me - at least in that way. I’m not entirely sure how I would do in a single-project setting where the company I worked for <em>was</em> the product and I wasn’t able to bounce around multiple projects if I wanted to, but I’m sure I would manage just fine.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Minty Boost! DubDub Edition]]></title>
    <link href="http://theonlylars.com/blog/2012/06/04/minty-boost-dubdub-edition/"/>
    <updated>2012-06-04T23:46:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://theonlylars.com/blog/2012/06/04/minty-boost-dubdub-edition</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Of all of the lists I have read about what to bring with you to WWDC, or suggestions on what veterans say you should do, the most consistent and unanimously present suggestion from all sources is that you will need to extend the battery life of your mobile device.  In the case of WWDC, there is a 99.99 (repeating, of course)% chance that it will be an iPhone. Being a procrastinator, I did not order one online like I should have from monoprice or similar.  Being a cheap, stingy software engineer, I refused to pay between $60-$100 for similar Li-Ion battery packs that carry anywhere from 3000-6500mAh of power. Being an electrical engineer by schooling, you tend to have <a href="http://www.ladyada.net/make/mintyboost/">stuff like this lying around the house</a>. Specifically, I had the minty boost powering an Arduino/Xbee assembly that is feeding temperature data from my HVAC exaust to Cosm.  You can read all about <em>that</em> <a href="/homedata">here</a>. It ultimately didn’t work for this application due to it’s limited supply time (only lasted about 6 hours at a time).</p>

<p>{% img center /images/posts/mintyboost/minty-boost-1.jpg %} This will enable me to use two rechargeable AA batteries at a time to at least get my iDevice back on it’s feet. I don’t intend for this to get me to a full charge, but it should suffice to get me to the next wall outlet.</p>

<p>Also, since Altoids does not make the Altoids gum that the Minty Boost was originally designed for, I had to improvise using some engineering magic:</p>

<p>{% img center /images/posts/mintyboost/minty-boost-2.jpg %}
This Eclipse mints container works perfectly for the Minty Boost, even if I did have to reverse the lid to get it to fit.</p>

<p>According to the battery rating, as well as the specs on the <a href="http://www.ifixit.com/Teardown/iPhone-4-Teardown/3130/1#s15307">iPhone’s battery</a> and <a href="http://www.ladyada.net/make/mintyboost/power.html">Adafruit’s own website</a>, I should be able to get about half a charge on two high-capacity NiMH AA batteries (the green Energizers shown above):</p>

<p>Input: <code>2 * 1.2V * 2450mAh * 80% = 4704 mWh</code></p>

<p>Output: <code>4704mWh/5V * 80% = 753 mAh</code></p>

<p>Charges: <code>1420 mAh iPhone 4 Capacity / 753 mAh = ~1/2</code> charge of iPhone 4 on two fresh AA rechargeable batteries</p>

<p>Good enough, I say.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Dub Dub]]></title>
    <link href="http://theonlylars.com/blog/2012/05/29/wwdc/"/>
    <updated>2012-05-29T22:19:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://theonlylars.com/blog/2012/05/29/wwdc</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Gettin’ ready for <a href="http://www.apple.com/wwdc">dub dub</a> in less than two weeks! By my count, there are 42 “To be announced” sessions on the schedule released today. You will find me at as many Core Animation, Core Graphics, and GCD sessions as I can attend, as well as all of the cool new API sessions.  To make the most of it all, I’ve been trying to think of some good questions for the framework engineers at the labs.  I’ll probably get some feedback on my <a href="http://larsacus.github.com/LARSAdController">ad controller</a>, as well as a new MBProgressHUD/SVProgressHUD-inspired HUD I’ve been working on at work, in addition to some other various work-related stuff.</p>

<p>Some new API’s stuffs I’m thinking/hoping we may see fill in the ‘to be announced’ blanks during the keynote:</p>

<ol>
  <li>Easier iCloud integration (don’t tell me you haven’t tried to integrate iCloud without issue)</li>
  <li>Notification Center widgets (I would even settle for a useful Notification Center)</li>
  <li>New maps APIs (<a href="http://www.macrumors.com/2012/05/29/composite-mockup-of-ios-6-maps-app-based-on-purported-leaked-screenshots/">Exhibit A</a>)</li>
  <li>More Core Image filters for iOS</li>
  <li>Fully-baked Siri (I don’t necessarily think we’ll see app-level Siri integration, just yet)</li>
  <li>Airplay&lt;-&gt;Mac integration</li>
  <li>Heck, I’m thinking there will be more generic OS-level mac-integration (think Airdrop)</li>
  <li>More twitter-like account integrations</li>
  <li>A new system-wide visual overhaul (not likely, but it’s been since iOS 4 that the look has changed in any way, and even that was minor)</li>
</ol>

<p>We’ll see how it all plays out.  I’ll be tweeting about it the whole time, NDA permitting, if you care to <a href="https://twitter.com/theonlylars">follow along</a>.</p>

<p>If you’re fortunate enough to be joining us all, then I’ll see you there!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
