<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: ads | hello. i'm @theonlylars]]></title>
  <link href="http://theonlylars.com/blog/categories/ads/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://theonlylars.com/"/>
  <updated>2012-12-17T22:01:34-06:00</updated>
  <id>http://theonlylars.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Lars Anderson]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[LARSAdController 3.0 RC]]></title>
    <link href="http://theonlylars.com/blog/2012/12/15/larsadcontroller-3-dot-0-rc/"/>
    <updated>2012-12-15T15:25:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://theonlylars.com/blog/2012/12/15/larsadcontroller-3-dot-0-rc</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>*Note: This is pre-release software and is still in-development. If you need a production version, please refer to the <a href="https://github.com/larsacus/LARSAdController">master branch</a> for production code.*</em></p>

<p>I’ve been working hard on refactoring <a href="https://github.com/larsacus/LARSAdController">LARSAdController 2.0</a> into a more modular and maintainable state over the past few months. I think it’s finally in a place that could warrant some final testing from other developers before being merged into the master branch. </p>

<p>Let’s take a look at what’s changed:</p>

<h2 id="a-new-class-prefix">A New Class Prefix</h2>
<p>I’ve been using the class prefix <code>LARS</code> for all of my open-source classes. While this really is short and unique, it’s always felt pretty egotistical to have my name plastered all over my classes. This is just how I feel from this side of the keyboard. Does it look the same from the user’s end? Let me know what you think.</p>

<p>Anyway, I’ve migrated new classes to the new <code>TOL</code> prefix, for <a href="https://twitter.com/theonlylars">@TheOnlyLars</a>. This feels more anonymous and I haven’t seen the prefix used by anyone else before, yet. I’d love to know if someone well known <em>is</em> using the <code>TOL</code> class prefix. If I feel like I like this prefix better, I may just start using it for everything.</p>

<p>I also like that it sounds like “toll”. I have grand visions of having some cool project named <code>TOLBooth</code>, <code>TOLRoad</code>, or <code>TOLHouse</code>. I can’t think of practical project ideas to put those names on, however.</p>

<h2 id="modular-ad-networks">Modular Ad Networks</h2>
<p>The big new feature for this release is modular ad networks. Ad junkies will know this as ad mediation. AdMob has an ad mediation framework, so does AdWhirl, MobClix, and others. This is my implementation. The actual mediation logic is in a single .h/.m file pair. The other files support the ad networks. I feel this is a very lightweight implementation compared to other company’s mediation platforms, not to mention it’s open source so you can peek under the hood to see how another developer has solved a problem.</p>

<p>Right now I’ve built ad network adapters for iAds and AdMob ads. These are the only two ad networks that I use in Droid Light, so I don’t know much about others, and these two seem to be the most popular for banner ads on iOS.</p>

<h3 id="house-ads">House Ads</h3>
<p>A third planned adapter I’m particularly excited about is an adapter for “house” ads, <em>but I have not started on it as of yet</em>. House ads would basically amount to an image and a tap destination that you supply yourself. It’s an ad for yourself. <!-- more -->This will ideally be loaded dynamically from a remote server somewhere so you won’t have to upload a new binary to the app store every time you want to change the ads.</p>

<p>You could have this house ad link to another page in your app, have it load a remote URL for another app you have in the app store, or even let users know a new version is available. This would be able to be mediated in just like any other ad network.</p>

<p>This is not necessarily part of this release, but is something that is going to be at least started by then.</p>

<h3 id="additional-ad-networks">Additional Ad Networks</h3>
<p>Additional ad networks can be easily created by conforming your <code>NSObject</code> subclass to the <code>TOLAdAdapter</code> protocol. As long as you have logging enabled, I feel the warnings and assertions, as well as the header documentation have been well-built enough to make this a pretty painless process.</p>

<h3 id="priority">Priority</h3>
<p>You can now prioritize which ad network you would like to have highest priority. Version 2.0 and prior had their priority fixed to have iAds serve first and have AdMob ads slaved to display when there was no available iAd inventory to display.</p>

<p>This worked for the first couple years of iAd as the eCPM and fill rate was so much better than anything else. Since iAds are basically paying out on par or worse than AdMob ads with way worse fill rates, you may not want to have iAds be your highest priority network. This is now possible.</p>

<h2 id="arc">ARC</h2>
<p><code>LARSAdController</code> 3.0 is now ARC-enabled. You’re welcome.</p>

<h2 id="presentation-types--pinning-location">Presentation Types &amp; Pinning Location</h2>
<p>In 2.0 and prior versions, you were limited to only displaying the ad at the bottom of your view and having it slide from the bottom as your animation. Two new properties have been added on <code>LARSAdController</code>: <code>presentationType</code> and <code>pinningLocation</code>.</p>

<h3 id="presentationtype">presentationType</h3>
<p>You now have the option to change the animation sliding direction of your ads when a new ad is loaded and animated on screen. You can have it slide in from any edge. I thought about adding different transition types (flip, etc.), but thought it really unnecessary unless this is something other’s think they want.</p>

<h3 id="pinninglocation">pinningLocation</h3>
<p>You also now have the option to change the physical location that the ad container lives on screen. In addition to the good ol’ bottom of your view, you can pin the ad to the top of the view. This is not revolutionary.</p>

<h2 id="a-view-controller-subclass">A View Controller Subclass</h2>
<p>I’ve created a new view controller subclass that is the <em>easiest</em> method to integrating ads into your view controller’s view. For simple configurations, simply having your view controller inherit from <code>TOLAdViewController</code> will display an ad on <code>viewDidLoad:</code>, just like is suggested in the setup instructions. Literally no other work is needed from you in the simplest case.</p>

<h3 id="conditionally-display-ads">Conditionally Display Ads</h3>
<p>If you need to conditionally display ads while using the view controller subclass, overriding <code>shouldDisplayAds</code> will enable you to add some logic to determine if the subclass should add the ad container to your view or not. If you return <code>NO</code>, then nothing else is performed and no ad is added to your view hierarchy. The base implementation always returns <code>YES</code>.</p>

<p>I am dogfooding this view controller to myself in Droid Light, so it works for more than just the trivial implementations.</p>

<h2 id="debug-logging">Debug Logging</h2>
<p>I’ve added pretty extensive debug logging for what’s currently constructed. If something goes wrong, you should be able to tell <em>what</em> is going on and on what line in what file. Runtime warnings are unconditionally displayed regardless of debug log state and should probably be taken care of.</p>

<p>To enable logs, simple define the <code>LARSADCONTROLLER_DEBUG</code> macro somewhere.</p>

<h1 id="help">Help?</h1>
<p>I primarily created <code>LARSAdController</code> because I was unsatisfied with the big ad mediation networks. They also felt pretty heavyweight and a lot of overhead to simply run two mediated ad networks on my low-traffic app<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup>. This is my simple solution to theirs.</p>

<p>This post is primarily asking for a handful of people to clone, implement, and just see if they see anything awry with their particular implementation needs. Detailed code samples and changes are on the README on the project repo’s branch, <a href="https://github.com/larsacus/LARSAdController/tree/AdapterAbstraction">AdapterAbstraction</a>.</p>

<p>You can find the <a href="https://github.com/larsacus/LARSAdController/tree/AdapterAbstraction">3.0 branch here</a> and file <a href="https://github.com/larsacus/LARSAdController/issues">issues here</a>. Don’t be shy about issues. If it’s not a bug, but simply something you didn’t expect and want clarification, file an issue.</p>

<p>If you’re so inclined, let me know what you think: <a href="https://twitter.com/theonlylars">@theonlylars</a></p>

<hr />
<div class="footnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1">
      <p>That and I <em>hate</em> when 3rd party libraries make me use the <code>-all_load</code> compiler flag<a href="#fnref:1" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Easily Integrate Your iOS App with iAd and AdMob]]></title>
    <link href="http://theonlylars.com/blog/2012/04/27/integrating-google-ads-with-iad/"/>
    <updated>2012-04-27T21:30:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://theonlylars.com/blog/2012/04/27/integrating-google-ads-with-iad</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I think Apple’s iAds had great potential.  But let’s face it.  They really aren’t pulling the weight they should.  When they do have inventory, however, they often make much more than any other ad service.  Let me show you how to not only quickly integrate iAds into your app, but do it properly all while using Google’s AdMob service as a backup.</p>

<p>If you watch Apple’s WWDC video on proper integration of iAd or read the iAd implementation documentation, you will see that they want you to use a single shared instance of your ads in all of your view controllers.  Since I also wanted that instance to be backed by Google ads when there was no iAd inventory, the best solution I could think of was the singleton.  This lead me to:</p>

<h2 id="introducing-larsadcontrollerhttpsgithubcomlarsacuslarsadcontroller">Introducing <a href="https://github.com/larsacus/LARSAdController">LARSAdController</a></h2>
<p>I built <a href="https://github.com/larsacus/LARSAdController">LARSAdController</a> in order to be a one-stop, single line integration of iAds (and later AdMob ads) into a <code>UIView</code>. I initially only supported iPods/iPhones in portrait orientation. It now has support for both iPods/iPhones as well as iPads in <em>any</em> orientation.</p>

<h2 id="integrating-larsadcontrollerhttpsgithubcomlarsacuslarsadcontroller">Integrating <a href="https://github.com/larsacus/LARSAdController">LARSAdController</a></h2>
<ol>
  <li>
    <p>First, you will need to clone the source from <a href="https://github.com/larsacus/LARSAdController">Github</a>:</p>

    <p><code>$ git clone git@github.com:larsacus/LARSAdController.git</code></p>

    <p>or add it as a git submodule:</p>

    <p><code>$ git submodule add git@github.com:larsacus/LARSAdController.git Vendor/LARSAdController</code></p>
  </li>
  <li>Add folder or <code>LARSAdController.m/h</code> to your project</li>
  <li>Download and copy the <a href="https://developers.google.com/mobile-ads-sdk/download#downloadios">Google ad SDK</a> into your project and go ahead and sign up for a Google publisher account at <a href="https://admob.com">AdMob.com</a> if you haven’t already</li>
  <li>Ensure the proper frameworks have been added to your application in order for iAds and AdMob ads to compile properly:
    <ol>
      <li>iAd.framework</li>
      <li>AudioToolbox.framework</li>
      <li>MessageUI.framework</li>
      <li>SystemConfiguration.framework</li>
    </ol>

    <p>You can add additional frameworks to your project in Xcode 4 by clicking on your project file in the project navigator on the left and going to <code>Build Phases &gt; Link Binary With Libraries &gt; Click + Symbol</code></p>

    <p>Whew! What a lot of stupid setup and we haven’t even written any code, yet! If you want to write code, you may be a little disappointed by this post, because there really isn’t any.</p>
  </li>
  <li>Now go to <code>Product &gt; Build</code> or type ‘⌘+B’ to build the project.  If your project builds without any errors, hurray! Skip to step 7.  If not, continue on…</li>
  <li>Surround your pullquote like this {" text to be quoted "}</li>
  <li><em>Now</em> we’re ready to write some code! Get your typing fingers ready, because text doesn’t just copy/paste itself! Add the following two lines of code to one of your view controller’s view lifecycle load or appear methods.  I’ve found that <code>viewWillAppear:</code> seems to be the best when pushing/popping view controllers with ads on them:</li>
</ol>

<p><div class='bogus-wrapper'><notextile><figure class='code'> <div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='objc'><span class='line'>  <span class="o">-</span> <span class="p">(</span><span class="kt">void</span><span class="p">)</span><span class="nl">viewWillAppear:</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="kt">BOOL</span><span class="p">)</span><span class="n">animated</span><span class="p">{</span>
</span><span class='line'>      <span class="p">[[</span><span class="n">LARSAdController</span> <span class="n">sharedManager</span><span class="p">]</span> <span class="nl">addAdContainerToView:</span><span class="n">self</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="n">view</span> <span class="nl">withParentViewController:</span><span class="n">self</span><span class="p">];</span>
</span><span class='line'>      <span class="p">[[</span><span class="n">LARSAdController</span> <span class="n">sharedManager</span><span class="p">]</span> <span class="nl">setGoogleAdPublisherId:</span><span class="n">myPublisherId</span><span class="p">];</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="p">}</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure></notextile></div></p>

<p>If you are only supporting a single orientation, or a single set of orientations (portrait/upside down portrait), then you’re basically done.  Just add the first single line of code to any view controller that you want to host ads in. Just be sure to call <code>setGoogleAdPublisherId:</code> the first time you add LARSAdController to a view. The ads will automatically be added to the bottom of the view and appear/hide whenever they have inventory available.</p>

<h2 id="multiple-orientations">Multiple Orientations</h2>

<p>If you would like to support multiple orientations, you will need to add the following line to the first call you make to add LARSAdController to a view:
<code>objc
    [[LARSAdController sharedManager] setShouldHandleOrientationChanges:YES];
</code></p>

<p>This will automatically listen for orientation changes and adjust the ad accordingly! See how easy that was! I told you if you were looking to type code, you were going to be disappointed.</p>

<p>Simply call the code in step 7 in any view you need the ad banner to be in, and it will automatically remove it from the old view and add it to the bottom of the new view.</p>

<h2 id="in-conclusion">In Conclusion</h2>
<p>I think this is an extremely easy, proper way just to implement iAds into your app, even if you aren’t using AdMob ads.  If you’re registered to use AdMob ads, then it’s an even <em>more</em> efficient method, as it’s only one line of code more in order to integrate and you will <em>always</em> have an ad displaying in your app.</p>

<p>If you’re using <a href="https://github.com/larsacus/LARSAdController">LARSAdController</a> in your app, I’d love to know. You can send me an email if you can find it, <a href="http://github.com/larsacus/LARSAdController">fork the repo</a> and change the readme on GitHub, or even better, just send me a quick note at <a href="http://twitter.com/theonlylars">@theonlylars</a> and I’ll add it to the README file.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
