<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: user-experience | theonlylars]]></title>
  <link href="http://theonlylars.com/blog/categories/user-experience/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://theonlylars.com/"/>
  <updated>2017-02-15T00:33:17-06:00</updated>
  <id>http://theonlylars.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Lars Anderson]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Microsoft HoloLens and Your Everyday Future]]></title>
    <link href="http://theonlylars.com/blog/2015/01/22/microsoft-hololens-and-your-everyday-future/"/>
    <updated>2015-01-22T11:36:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://theonlylars.com/blog/2015/01/22/microsoft-hololens-and-your-everyday-future</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>Having not posted on here in over a year, it feels good to write again.</em></p>

<p>Yesterday, Microsoft announced and demoed a surprising, radical new project called <a href="http://www.microsoft.com/microsoft-hololens">HoloLens</a>. If you haven’t seen it yet, please go the Microsoft site and glance at it to make the rest of this make sense. The essence behind HoloLens is a goggle-like device you wear over your eyes that projects holograms augmented into your perception of reality – wirelessly. Technology like this is significant for a few reasons that may not be immedately apparent when looking at the demos they have provided. This technology today, itself may look a little socially isolating, may just be a necessary stepping stone to what we will soon know as the ‘present’ of computing.</p>

<p>As much as it surprises me to say this to myself about Microsoft, but it’s a little refreshing to see Microsoft show off this kind of technology and not Google.</p>

<h2 id="close-your-eyes">Close Your Eyes</h2>
<p>Close your eyes. Now imagine what the future looks like to you. You may be picturing your favorite science-fiction movie like <em>Minority Report</em> or <em>Blade Runner</em>. Usually there are screens everywhere. Computing is so cheap we can make displays out of and integrate them into almost anything – giant displays on the side of a building, displays integrated into walls, clothing, or other materials.</p>

<p>Maybe this is the case. But <em>what if</em> the future of this functional reality is just a little bit closer than that?<!-- more --> Yes, maybe we will have screens everywhere, but what if only you could see those screens? What if the requirement for those screens to be physically present were removed? You look to your left and right – there are holographic screens projected everywhere just like you imagined the future.</p>

<h2 id="too-much-information">Too Much Information?</h2>
<p>If the future has screens everywhere, would you not simply be overwhelmed with the information being presented on those screens? As a thought-application of this, let’s imagine we are driving down the road in our personal automobile. A virtual screen is “projected” over most every surface within eye’s-reach. As a direct translation of the current physical configuration of your car, you may immediately imagine your speed or navigation being on these virtual screens – maybe even the current music playing or your calendar from your phone.</p>

<p>Let’s glipse the in-car experience in a different light, since many engineering constraints of the automobile driver’s UX paradigm has completely shifted: The A-pillar is replaced with a projection of what lies just behind it. Your car door becomes transparent just like your A-pillar to reveal a small motorcycle in your blind spot. Your vehicle’s on-board radar (something already existing on some vehicles) is pulling double-duty in a massive snow-storm to project a better picture of the cars that lie just out of your visible range. The near-future of driving may not be “more screens” with useless, distracting information – it may actually be an <em>extension</em> of your reality by bypassing the physical constraints we already have on our world, making us <em>more aware</em> by providing more natural, easily digestible information.</p>

<p>Fighter pilots have been using a variant of this technology in their helmets for awhile now in order to provide them with more relevent, contextual information while piloting a $100M aircraft. The purpose of such a technology is to provide someone with <em>more information</em> in such a way that is easy to process for the user. Something like this is a brand-new area of user-experience for the everyman.</p>

<h2 id="creation">Creation</h2>
<p>One of the applications shown in the demo videos was in content creation. A designer sits next to a computer with a holographic projection of their work sitting next to them on the desk. They then walk over to a 1:1 scale model of their work to feel the presence of their work as they walk around it, tweaking parameters as if they were using their 3D CAD software.</p>

<p>Is this not the natural progression of where computing, content creation and design should be headed? Technology should <em>enable</em> humans to create, not get in the way with IDEs, keystrokes or even screens. This is exactly what car designers do now with clay models and styrofoam, just on a more physical, tedious scale.</p>

<h2 id="tomorrows-computing-today">Tomorrow’s Computing Today?</h2>
<p><a href="http://worrydream.com">Brett Victor</a> <a href="http://worrydream.com/#!/Bio">has a mission</a> to explore and guide the future of “technology” as it applies to human interaction. In his talk, <a href="http://vimeo.com/115154289">“The Humane Representation of Thought”</a>, he talks about the current state of programming (and maybe even computing in general) being “inhumane”. As a programmer, I can’t disagree with this: A human being sits in front of a computer for 8-10 hours a day, entering individual characters into a computer telling it very explicitly what to do – basically glorified data entry with a dash of creationism and creativity. These characters get translated into all of the things we use everyday we know generically as software. Everything from text editors to 3D CAD software – all built the same.</p>

<p>Brett explores how future technologies should integrate with human interactions to make the experience richer and more engaging, not less engaging. This is something that Microsoft’s HoloLens is definitely a step <em>toward</em> – at least in the richness and interaction factors. We still don’t get any of the physical feedback mechanisms that, for instance, paper and pencil have. “The Humane Representation of Thought” is an excellent watch if you have time, as well as his talks “<a href="http://worrydream.com/DrawingDynamicVisualizationsTalk/">Drawing Dynamic Visualizations</a>” and “<a href="http://worrydream.com/StopDrawingDeadFish/">Stop drawing dead fish</a>” since they both relate to human-computer interaction and the way we should think about computing in the future.</p>

<h2 id="but-i-would-never-wear-that-in-public">“But I Would Never Wear That In Public”</h2>
<p>Surround your pullquote like this {&#8221; text to be quoted &#8220;}</p>

<h2 id="applications">Applications</h2>

<h3 id="augmentation">Augmentation</h3>
<p>The initial application of this device is going be more along the lines of “computing augmentation”. These are the experience “hacks” that directly translate your current computing environment and paradigms into your physical world, just like some of Microsoft’s own demos show off. This includes the scenarios where a designer is creating a physical model, a researcher is exploring mars, gaming applications and even the integration of other physical people in your augmented world with you (think remote collaboration).</p>

<p>Another set of immediate applications includes “piloting” activities (driving a motorcycle or car, driving heavy machinery, etc) or sports such as skiing or mountain biking.</p>

<h3 id="new-paradigms">New Paradigms</h3>
<p>Subsequent, evolved applications of this technology will depend on the v2+ physical devices that are created to project the holographs. This is when you might could get into the everyday integration of HoloLens as a personal device if the technology is able to get out of the way enough to enable this. It is at this point in which we will see applications of holographic technology used in ways we can’t easily grasp now since our minds don’t yet build products or applications that use this technology natively.</p>

<h2 id="microsoft-as-the-future"><em>Microsoft</em> as the Future?</h2>
<p>Surround your pullquote like this {&#8221; text to be quoted &#8220;}</p>

<p>We should also take note from Brett Victor, to shape new innovations not to let technology dictate how the future will look, but guide and humanize future technology in a way that will better our lives and connect us with others. If this isn’t the future, this is at least a glimpse down the path of the future of computing.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Abandoning the Consumer: Ignoring User Experience]]></title>
    <link href="http://theonlylars.com/blog/2013/03/11/abandoning-the-consumer-ignoring-user-experience/"/>
    <updated>2013-03-11T16:36:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://theonlylars.com/blog/2013/03/11/abandoning-the-consumer-ignoring-user-experience</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>Fair Warning: This post is relatively <a href="https://www.google.com/search?hl=en&amp;tbm=nws&amp;q=simcity">SimCity</a>-centric.</em></p>

<p>The title includes some strong words, yes - but you do not want your users even <em>feeling</em> forgotten about. In my line of work, the user is a very central part of the development cycle. This is true in part to the intimate nature of the software I write. My software travels with the user. Everywhere the user goes - my software is living in their pocket. In fact, not only is it always with the user, but the user may also be using my software in a specific environment. How the user uses and interfaces with my software is what is known as the <em>user experience</em>. It has nothing to do with what the UI looks like, the shadow angle of the button when pressed or the ‘flat’ nature of the design.</p>

<h2 id="the-users-experience-as-a-requirement">The User’s Experience as a Requirement</h2>
<p>In today’s market, the user is becoming ever more selective about the applications that they use and is raising the standards to which they will use when selecting their software using. Some of us have very specific quips about what they consider a “deal-breaker”. For me, this could be something like not making your app iPhone 5 enabled when it supports iOS 5.0+ or when you still don’t have retina assets for your app. This is inexcusable. I have heard others say that they hate when apps hijack the status bar for their own temporary in-app status. I personally love how that looks.</p>

<p>The above is said to emphasize that consumers care now more than ever about how their software both looks, feels, behaves, and how they can use it. If your users feel confused, nickel-and-dimed, or find using your software in any way difficult, they will most likely <em>not use it anymore</em>. Moreover, they will not tell their friends about it. If you screw up badly enough, they will actively tell their friends to avoid your software altogether.<!-- more --></p>

<p>So taking this into consideration for your product, your business goals should be (in this order):</p>

<ol>
  <li>Make the user’s life as easy as possible (UX)</li>
  <li>Look good doing it (UI design)</li>
  <li>Make money ($) as a result of 1 &amp; 2</li>
</ol>

<p>Master these and you end up with companies like Apple, who are <em>so</em> intently focused on the user’s experience, they have a team that does nothing but <a href="http://www.networkworld.com/community/node/79642">design and test the box for the “best” experience when opening your new iPhone</a>.</p>

<h2 id="the-game-industry">The Game Industry</h2>
<p>The game industry is an incredibly complex industry. I don’t pretend to be a game developer, publisher or in any way know the business ends of the gaming industry. However, I <em>am</em> a PC gamer and a software engineer in the business of pleasing my users. I have been a PC gamer since the DOS days, and I’m really not that old. I bring this up to say that I believe the game industry seems to be rapidly devolving when speaking in terms of the user’s experience. They do all of this in the name of “piracy”<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote">1</a></sup>.</p>

<h3 id="drm">DRM</h3>
<p>The specific example of user-experience gone awry in the game industry is with DRM (digital rights management). This literally has nothing to do with any game individually and has everything to do with access control to a specific resource. The idea behind DRM being that the user is given an obstacle course of hoops and conditions to satisfy before they are given access to the resource (the game) they paid for. This is to prevent people who have <em>not</em> paid for the game from using the resource.</p>

<p>Some companies make DRM extremely transparent and pain-free. Steam is a company I will throw money at all day (happily, I might add) to buy games from because I <em>feel</em> that they are truly trying to make my experience playing games as easy as possible. DRM keys are automatically stored for me and prompted at me when I first launch a game. Even then, most of the time, I don’t even need to do anything additional to play my games except download and launch them.</p>

<p>Others actively go out of their way to ensure that the minimum number of people will pirate the game. This comes at the direct expense of all of their paying customers. In the same fashion that you have to sit through three un-skippable FBI warnings before watching a movie that you just bought, gamers have to satisfy all of the DRM requirements of their games before they can play them. In the specific example of SimCity, they must always be online and authenticated to the internet to play what has (until now) always been a single-player centric game.</p>

<h2 id="ea-and-simcity">EA and SimCity</h2>
<p><em>This is my personal account of my (user) experience with EA and it’s brand-new “blockbuster”, SimCity.</em></p>

<p>I have been really excited about SimCity for a long time, so I preordered it. The only place it is available to play is directly through EA’s subpar Origin client. I paid for the “digital” version on Origin. I later found out that they <a href="https://help.ea.com/article/returns-and-cancellations">do not offer refunds</a> for digitally downloaded products and in fact <a href="http://www.cinemablend.com/games/EA-Officially-Halts-SimCity-Refunds-Polygon-Drops-Review-Score-Even-Lower-53444.html">will ban your account</a> if you follow through with a chargeback - it’s just their policy. You can, however, get a refund from Amazon if you buy it there. On launch day I started the download before work and then came home and was going to fire it up to play it. This was just the beginning.</p>

<h3 id="initial-user-experience">Initial User Experience</h3>
<p>On first launch I was greeted with this lovely screen. <img class="right" src="/images/simcity1.jpg" width="300" height="300">A list of servers that I was not allowed to get on. Getting on a server is a prerequisite to playing the game since the SimCity servers do a couple of things:</p>

<ol>
  <li>Authenticate that you paid for the game</li>
  <li>Store everything in the cloud all of the time</li>
  <li>Offload part of the computational simulation to their servers so it’s impossible to play offline</li>
</ol>

<p>The first is simply annoying and is done every time you launch the game and continuously from then on. The second should be in addition to storing your data locally. The third <a href="http://www.rockpapershotgun.com/2013/03/11/simcity-is-inherently-broken-lets-not-let-this-go/">should have been killed off</a> during product discovery for the game mechanics 6 years ago before any code was written.</p>

<p>I personally ran into just about every issue that I heard others talk about online:</p>

<ol>
  <li>Could not authenticate with the server</li>
  <li>Could not load into the tutorial city</li>
  <li>Once I loaded the tutorial city, the tutorial is evidently loaded from their servers, so the city was unusable since every button was disabled, however the music was very nice. The entire game was basically useless</li>
  <li>Claiming new cities was not available, since even claiming a “private” region is done online</li>
  <li>Second day - Was able to claim a new region and play for a while - tutorial still useless. Some crashes and hit-or-miss (mostly miss) loading.</li>
  <li>Third day - Was able to play mostly, but now with all of the <a href="http://www.joystiq.com/2013/03/07/non-critical-simcity-features-disabled-to-improve-server-issue/">features that had been removed in the latest update</a> (cheetah mode, achievements, some region filtering, etc.). What EA determined were “non-core” features.</li>
  <li><a href="http://www.reddit.com/r/SimCity/comments/1a0taq/compiled_list_of_suggestions_and_bug_reports_to/">Simulation bugs galore</a></li>
</ol>

<h3 id="spin-dr">Spin Dr.</h3>
<p>This experience was not isolated, which resulted in a ungodly amount of negative discussions on twitter. Last I checked, the <a href="http://www.metacritic.com/game/pc/simcity/user-reviews">game’s user-score on MetaCritic</a> was a paltry 1.6/10. The coveted “Critic” score is (currently) at <a href="http://www.metacritic.com/game/pc/simcity/critic-reviews">68/100</a>. Amazon even halted digital sales of the game and put up a “notice” to users buying the game of server issues that would prevent users from playing the game altogether. Polygon has even gone so far as to <a href="http://www.polygon.com/game/simcity-2013/2630#review_update_3840603">amend their review of the game</a> several times and now sits at a 4/10 down from a pre-launch 9/10. EA has even actively told it’s marketing partners to <a href="http://www.ign.com/articles/2013/03/08/simcity-marketing-pulled-by-ea">halt all promotion for SimCity</a> altogether. It was also rumored <a href="http://www.p4rgaming.com/?p=1473">EA was paying hundreds of Chinese spammers</a> to write positively about the game online.</p>

<p>I could go on, but it’s really not necessary. Consumer trust and general distaste for anything your company produces is a difficult thing to recover from: “Hey have you heard of that new game EA is putting out?” “Yeah, it looked pretty cool, but do you remember what they did to the <em>last</em> one?” “Oh yeah, that sucks.”</p>

<p>What happens in 10 years when EA decides continuing to run their servers is extremely cost prohibitive? I hope you like SimCity 2000.</p>

<h2 id="users-dont-forget-being-bitten">Users Don’t Forget Being Bitten</h2>
<p>EA and Maxis forgot one very important component of their game: the users. In an effort to maximize the number of people who would legitimately play the game, they made the experience so horrible and cumbersome for those who would pay legitimately for their product. Not only this, but the users are <em>forced</em> to play under a very specific set of circumstances, namely, always having a reliable internet connection.</p>

<p>I am curious to know what the dollar value is for the following two line-items on EA’s financial balance sheet:</p>

<ol>
  <li>The cost of development &amp; implementation of complex anti-piracy DRM measures and server infrastructure, as well as the cost of the loss of brand loyalty and trust to users as a result of poor user experience</li>
  <li>The potential cost of losses to pirated copies of the game</li>
</ol>

<p>If 1 &lt; 2, then rest assured you’ll be seeing much more of the above in the game industry in the years to come. As for me personally, I am going to actively go out of my way to not buy anything from EA as much as I can in the future. Or maybe they simply <em>assume</em> 1 &lt; 2 and are just too big to care.</p>

<p>In the case of SimCity, the users <em>are</em> feeling forgotten about. They <em>will</em> lose your brand’s trust when you take advantage of them.</p>

<h2 id="user-experience-from-the-top-down">User Experience from the Top-Down</h2>
<p>The user’s experience shouldn’t just be those that are designing a product’s responsibility. You can have all of the most talented user-experience product gurus in the world, but if your management, marketing, and primary stakeholders (money people) don’t understand this, the entire product’s experience will reflect only those that the user remembers (the bad ones). The user experience, when left out, is what turns otherwise exceptional products into those that are at best mediocre.</p>

<p>Don’t abandon the consumer. After all, they <em>are</em> the ones giving you their money.</p>

<p><em>My personal recommendation for SimCity? Wait for the game to go on sale. While the game is moderately fun in its current state, it’s not as fun as it could be with all of the server issues worked out, not to mention all of the bugs and crippled features. Maybe by then we’ll have an offline mode to play while on an airplane or bus.</em></p>

<div class="footnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1">
      <p>Other industries do this, too, don’t get me wrong <a href="#fnref:1" class="reversefootnote">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
